<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian concord: or S. Pauls parallel between the body natural and mystical. Exemplified in a sermon preacht in the cathedral church of S. Paul, on Sunday the 13th. of January 1660. By Matthevv Griffith D.D.</title>
            <author>Griffith, Matthew, 1599?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85706</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866946</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119235</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240917471</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1081_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207929</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866946</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99866946e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85706)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119235)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 161:E1081[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian concord: or S. Pauls parallel between the body natural and mystical. Exemplified in a sermon preacht in the cathedral church of S. Paul, on Sunday the 13th. of January 1660. By Matthevv Griffith D.D.</title>
                  <author>Griffith, Matthew, 1599?-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by W.G. for T. Firby at Grayes-in-gate in Holborn,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 8.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Paul, --  the Apostle, Saint --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christianity --  Essence, genius, nature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119235:1"/>
            <p>Christian Concord: OR, S. Pauls Parallel BETWEEN The Body <hi>NATƲRAL</hi> and <hi>MYSTICAL.</hi> EXEMPLIFIED IN A SERMON Preacht in the Cathedral Church of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> On Sunday the 13<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> of <hi>January</hi> 1660.</p>
            <p>By MATTHEVV GRIFFITH D. D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil. 2.-5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If there be therefore any consolation in Christ if any comfort of love, if any fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercies; fulfil ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the same love, being of one accord, of one mind.</p>
               <p>Let nothing be done through strife, or vain glory, but in lowliness of mind, let each esteem other better then themselves.</p>
               <p>Look not every man on his own things, but every man also on the things of others.</p>
               <p>Let this mind be in you, which was in Christ Jesus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 18.37.</hi>
               </bibl> To this end was I born, and for this cause came I into the world, that I should bear witness to the truth: every one that is of the truth, hears my voice.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W.G.</hi> for <hi>T. Firby</hi> at <hi>Grayes-In-gate</hi> in <hi>Holborn.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119235:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119235:2"/>
            <head>TO S<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> EDWARD NICHOLAS Knight, Principal <hi>Secretary</hi> of <hi>State</hi> to His MAIESTIE, And one of His MAIESTIE'S Most Honourable <hi>Privy-Councel.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have hitherto had so small Encouragement for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing my good Affections both to <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> that upon just Grounds I had resolved to adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture no more on the <hi>Press:</hi> For though I never gave way to the Printing of more <hi>Sermons</hi> then two, the former out of a
<pb facs="tcp:119235:3"/> sincere desire to have prevented the late Commotions; and the latter to promote <hi>His MAIESTIES just Restitution</hi>) Yet all the thankes I reaped (such was then the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of the Times) was, to be committed to <hi>Newgate</hi> for both; and this unequal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution for so pious intentions and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able endeavours, had rendred me very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to appear again in Print. Yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lately appointed by my <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> (whose courage, and vigilancie make him fit for, and worthy of the grat trust which he now so faithfully dischargeth) to preach this <hi>Sermon;</hi> I have been in some sort enforced to publish it, partly to satisfie the incessant and unavoydable importunitie of many <hi>noble Friends,</hi> and <hi>well-affected Hearers;</hi> and partly to prevent being mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>represented by such short-Writers, as hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken my Notes, told me plainly, that if I would not print this <hi>Sermon,</hi> they would, in order to the publick good; so that I must needs say it is not entreated, but extorted; and yet I shall make this Vertue of that Necessity, to let the World
<pb facs="tcp:119235:3"/> see in this <hi>poor Dedication,</hi> not onely how grateful I desire to approve my self to your <hi>Honour,</hi> For your daily repeated <hi>Favours;</hi> but also that your Prudence and Integritie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Candour and Charitie, are such a <hi>Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>Ornament to the Court,</hi> that they alone are sufficient both to defend it from Conspiracie, and to denominate it <hi>truely Christian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your <hi>Honour</hi> hath by many and many <hi>Acts</hi> acquired such an habit of doing what is <hi>just,</hi> and <hi>Right, that</hi> (as it was said of <hi>Cato</hi>) you cannot do otherwise. You dispatch <hi>State-affairs</hi> with so much inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitie, and dexteritie, that what other <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians</hi> Languished under as too hard a labour, is but your ordinarie Recreation; who have not onely learn't, (with <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mistocles</hi>) but are able to teach the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die way how to make a small <hi>Common-wealth</hi> great, and of a <hi>sick Bodie poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,</hi> a <hi>sound one:</hi> and your singular abilities will now as spectably appear in repairing <hi>our breaches,</hi> and <hi>healing our distempers,</hi> as the best <hi>Pilot's skill</hi> doth
<pb facs="tcp:119235:4"/> in <hi>a Storm,</hi> and the <hi>Gallantry</hi> of a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> in a <hi>Battle;</hi> though being <hi>a Star</hi> of the first Magnitude, the Greater you are, the less you seeme, by reason of the distance between you and us. All that know you, must acknowledge that no <hi>Prince</hi> ever had a more deserving, and obliging Servant, who preferres his Great <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Masters</hi> Honour, before his own Interest; and in these cloudie times to give him light, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumes himself. In your single person his <hi>Sacred MAIESTY</hi> hath all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of a <hi>Full</hi> and <hi>Faithful Councel.</hi> All your <hi>Oracles</hi> are so sweetly, and evenly tempered of <hi>Policie</hi> and <hi>Pietie,</hi> (your <hi>Honour</hi> being <hi>wise as a Serpent, Innocent as a Dove</hi>) that <hi>Josephs Character,</hi> in the <hi>23.</hi> of Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> at the <hi>50.</hi> is not onely proper to you but in some sence, peculiar, Viz. <hi>An honourable Counsellour, a good man and a just; one that consen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not to the councell and deed of them, waiting for the Kingdome of God.</hi> Your own Laudable Actions commend you far beyond my invention, and expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions;
<pb facs="tcp:119235:4"/> yet Gratitude prompts me to have added my <hi>Mite,</hi> to your <hi>gracious Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surie,</hi> but that I have constantly observed that you had rather be, and do things, worthy of <hi>praise,</hi> then hear of either: And so not doubting that your Honour will as chearfully accept of this small pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, as you have been ever accustomed to do things great, and glorious; I humbly crave both your <hi>patronage</hi> and <hi>pardon</hi> for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption; and rest,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yourr Honours most humble Servant, MATTHEW GRIFFITH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:119235:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119235:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 12.4, 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>For as we have many Members in one Body; and all the Members have not the same Office: So we, being many, are one Body in Christ; and each of us Members one of another.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Blessed Lord and Saviour (in the</hi> 12. <hi>Chapter of St.</hi> Luke, <hi>at the</hi> 42. <hi>Verse) styles him a faithful and wise Steward, that gives his Houshold their portion of meat in due season. The ordinary Dispensers of the Word and Sacraments, are called his Stewards (in the</hi> 4. <hi>Chapter of the first Epistle to the Corinthians,) The great Congregation in the beauty of Holyness, is his Houshold: Such select Scriptures as holy Church hath appointed for the proper Lessons, the Epistles and the Gospels to be read on the several Sundayes and Festivals throughout the year, are the portion of meat: And the Orthodoxe explication and application of them to all emergencies of time and occasions, is to do</hi> Opus Diei in die suo, <hi>to speak a word in season. And according to this Catholick sense, I hope I shall now set before your Lordship, and the rest Dearly beloved, such a portion of holy Writ as will appear upon a full and favourable hearing to be both seasoned and seasonable: For
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119235:6"/> my text is a principal part of the Epistle for this very day, and so it is seasonable; and the cheif Scope of this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is to comend unto us Christian Unity and Unanimity, who (the greater is our Sin and Shame) have been of late, and still are, too too much distracted, and divided among our selves; and in this regard my Text (whether it be looked upon either as a cordial, or a corasive) must be confessed to be well seasoned: and therefore I shall need to make no other apology for my choice of this Text at this time, then one of the Antient Fathers did upon the like occasion,</hi> Deus tam faciat Scripturam commodam quam est accommoda; <hi>The Lord by his Spirit of grace make this Scripture as profitable to you, as ere I have fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed my Discourse, it will appear at this time to be proper for you. And so I fall close to the words of my Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>MY Text begins with a <hi>Nam,</hi> for; and a <hi>Sicut,</hi> as: For as; this <hi>For,</hi> is connective; and this <hi>As</hi> is comparative. By this <hi>For,</hi> our Apostle would prove that which he had asserted in the Verse before, <hi>viz.</hi> That we must not be over-wise but sober-wise; or wise to Sobriety. In which his mind and meaning is to bring all men to be contented with such parts of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and gifts of grace, as God hath been pleased to give them; and he would have them to use and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove these Talents, with all possible humility and charity, to the edification of their Christian brethren; and not for any oblique respects whatsoever, to make a Schism in the Church, as some self-conceited per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons then had done, to the losse of peace and truth on Earth and of Glory in the Heavens.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119235:6"/>
            <p>And this our Apostle here both amplifies, and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrates by a pithy and pertinent comparison, bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the natural body, and applied to Christs body mystical. And as this <hi>For</hi> is a Conjunction cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal, so St. <hi>Paul</hi> intends thereby to shew cause why we should all be sober-minded; and the cause is implied in this <hi>Sicut [As]</hi> with which it is coupled: Conceive then our Apostle making his transition, by this <hi>For;</hi> and both proving and clearing his former doctrine, by this <hi>Sicut, As;</hi> which is an Adverb of Likenesse, and a Note of Similitude.</p>
            <p>And some of the Ancients have observed to my hand, that comparisons in Scripture are of excellent use, and serve both to explain and adorn such truths, as being intellectual and abstruse, are not in and of themselves obvious to men of ordinary capacity. Both the Prophets and Apostles are full of them; Yea our blessed Lord himself is in nothing so frequent, as in these <hi>Similies</hi> and <hi>Sicuts;</hi> and so are all the Fathers: <hi>Similitudinem vobis adhibeam,</hi> saith St. <hi>Augustine de verbis Domini,</hi> Let me use a Similitude unto you, that what you do not so clearly understand, may be made easie by a familiar instance. And St <hi>Chrysostome</hi> did so superabound in this kind, that some <hi>Neoteriques</hi> have made it their work, to collect, and reduce all his allusions to proper heads, by way of Common places; for the better imbellishing of such mens discourses, as are jejune, and barren of Invention: and as you shall meet with many other parables, and similitudes; so with none more apt, and elegant, then this of the <hi>Body</hi> and the <hi>Members:</hi> and what energie there is in this comparison, may be gathered from the wholsom effect it took among the Commons of <hi>Rome,</hi> to whom<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119235:7"/>
               <hi>Menennius Agrippa</hi> propounded only this Similitude; and therewith pacified the tumultuous rabble; as <hi>Livie</hi> in the Second of his <hi>Decads,</hi> relates it on this wise.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Upon a time</hi> (saith he) <hi>the Members complained of the Stomach or Belly; that they devoured all, yet did no work and because they seemed not to labour like the rest of the parts, the Members conspired among themselves to feed them no longer; and the Stomach not taking in due suste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the Eyes ere long waxed dimme; the Ears deaf, the Hands and Arms grew weak and feeble; the Legs were scarce able to stand, or the feet to stirre; briefly all the Members became Epileptick, and the whole body consumed for want of nourishment: and the Members being sensible of this Atrophie, they soon recanted their Errour and fell close to feeding the Stomach again, as being convinced by sad experience, that howere the Stomach seems not to take pains, and to labour like the other parts, yet when it is duely fed and faustered, the whole body fares the better for it, because it feeds not only for it self, but what it takes in it digests, and so sends forth nourishment unto the rest of the Members; and by this seasonable Apologue the mutinous multitude was appeased, and fairly reduced to their former subjection and obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what the Oratour there applied to that Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> which he looked upon as the Stomach of the Body politique: Our Apostle here adapts to Christs Body mystical; and under this comparison, he infers two things for the better confirming of what he had before delivered.</p>
            <p>The one is, that every man hath his measure of gifts in the Church; seeing that each man is but as it were a particular Member of the Body mystical: and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119235:7"/> therefore as the hand is not capable of seeing, neither the foot of hearing; so, <hi>Non omnia possumus omnes:</hi> For Almighty God, who is a most free Agent, hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted each man both his measure, and his stint: some have more (as in the Parable of the Talents) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credited unto them, some fewer; every one hath some, but none hath all; as in the Proverb, <hi>Unus Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardus non vidit omnia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other is, That every man must be sober-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and modestly conceited of his own parts, and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; seeing that what ere his gifts be, yet in one kind or other, he hath as much need of others as they can have of him; though perhaps they be not so highly pearch'd and prefer'd; yet they may be altogether as needful, and useful in their way, as himself.</p>
            <p>And therefore as all the <hi>members</hi> of the <hi>body</hi> doe sweetly accord together in their distinct Functions, each standing in need of the others help: so in the Church each true <hi>member</hi> thereof should tend to the good of all the rest; without either envying their Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, or incroaching upon their <hi>Office.</hi> Thus no less piously, then prudently, doth our Apostle take order to prevent both emulation, and usurpation, when he saith in the Text; <hi>For as we have many members in one body, &amp; all the members have not the same office,</hi> so we &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In which words, let me commend to your Chaistian attention and intention two principal parts, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Proposition; <hi>Et</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and a Reddition, or the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern; and the parallel: and in each of them we have three things considerable; <hi>For,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the former main part, which I call the Proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, our Apostle by way of comparison set's down the excellent state of man's <hi>body</hi> in three respects; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119235:8"/>
            <p>First, in regard of it's unity; <hi>for,</hi> the <hi>body</hi> is but <hi>one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in regard of plurality of parts; <hi>for,</hi> it hath many <hi>members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, In regard of diversity of Functions; <hi>for,</hi> all the <hi>members have not the same Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the latter main part, which I call the Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Our Apostle delivers three things proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to those that I have already hinted: <hi>for,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, as there he shewed that the natural <hi>body</hi> is <hi>one;</hi> so here, applying it to the Church, he shewes that the <hi>body</hi> mystical is but <hi>one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, As there he saith that this one natural <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> hath many <hi>members;</hi> so here he saith, that we are many in <hi>Christs body</hi> mystical.</p>
            <p>Lastly, As there he assumes that the divers <hi>members</hi> of the natural <hi>body</hi> have not the same <hi>Office:</hi> so here he applies it by demonstrating that <hi>We are members one of another in Christ's body mystical;</hi> and consequently by the Law of the <hi>body,</hi> and the <hi>members</hi> of the same, we are all strictly bound to be mutually helpful each to other, in the faithful discharge of all Ecclesiastical and Spiritual duties.</p>
            <p>These are the six wings of this <hi>Seraphim,</hi> which are now spread over you; or rather these six be the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable branches of this Tree of Life; whose fruit (by Gods assistance) I come now to shake off, and you are to gather up as they fall: and I begin with the first particular of the first main part, <hi>Viz.</hi> The Unity of the <hi>body</hi> natural; for so saith our Apostle here, <hi>Sicut,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>As the body is one,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And though Saint <hi>Paul</hi> speakes here with a <hi>Sicut,</hi> and by way of comparison; yet elsewhere he delivers
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119235:8"/> this as a positive Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>body is but one;</hi> as in the 12. Chapter of the first Epistle to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> at the 26. verse; and in the 4. Chapter to the <hi>Ephesians,</hi> at the 4. verse, <hi>There is on body,</hi> &amp;c. And I presume this will be easily granted: and yet how, and in what sence <hi>the body is one,</hi> seeing it consists of so <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny members,</hi> I find it among the Schoolmen very much disputed; who observe that things may be said to be <hi>one</hi> divers wayes: <hi>For,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, There is an Unitie which is made by collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; thus many stones laid together make <hi>one</hi> heap.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is an Unity which is made by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction; Thus Man and Wife make but one person in Law; and are but <hi>one flesh</hi> in the Gospel; for our Saviour saith, in the 19. of <hi>Matthew</hi> at the 6. verse, <hi>that they remain no longer two, but one flesh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is an Unity in numeration; Thus God is stiled <hi>One,</hi> in the 6. Chap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> at the 4. verse, <hi>The Lord our God is one Lord. He is one</hi> and <hi>onely one.</hi> And as in <hi>Arithmetick</hi> all numbers flow from Unity: so in <hi>Theologie</hi> all creatures do from God, and in him they terminate, that <hi>He may be all in all,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.28.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, There is an Unity which results from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy; which makes men in all estates and conditions, still one and the same; thence grew the Motto, <hi>sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per idem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, There is an Unity which is made by consent in matters of Religion; Thus in the 4. chapter of the <hi>Acts,</hi> at the 32. verse; <hi>The multitude of them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved were of one heart, and one soul,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, There is an Unity which is made by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion; thus our Apostle (speaking of such an <hi>one</hi> as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119235:9"/> sincerely cleaves to God in Christ) saith that he is <hi>one spirit with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, There is an Unity which is made by vouchsafing; as in the first chapter of Saint <hi>John</hi> at the 14. verse, <hi>when the Word was made flesh, he was truely stiled</hi> Emanuel, <hi>God with us;</hi> God and Man in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Person.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, There is an Unity which is spoken either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitely, as the 22. of Saint <hi>Luke;</hi> and <hi>one of them smote the servant,</hi> &amp;c. Or by way of excellency; for our Saviour told the Jewes, <hi>There is one that accuseth you,</hi> &amp;c. Thus <hi>Unus homo nobis,</hi> &amp;c. saith the <hi>Lyrique</hi> Poet, meaning <hi>Fabius,</hi> who <hi>cunctando restituit rem.</hi> Or by way of reproach: Thus <hi>Judas</hi> the Traytour is call'd <hi>One of the twelve,</hi> in the 14. chapter of Saint <hi>Mark,</hi> at the 10. verse: <hi>Unus,</hi> saith Saint <hi>Hierome, numero non merito.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, there is an unity which springs both from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, and integrality, thus both the body natural is <hi>one,</hi> though it consists of diverse parts; and the Church is also <hi>one,</hi> though compacted of never so <hi>many members;</hi> and so you see what kind of Unity this is in the Text; and herein you may withal observe.</p>
            <p>First, The never enough admired Wisedome of God, who of two so dissimilar parts as are the <hi>body</hi> and the <hi>soul,</hi> the <hi>flesh</hi> and the <hi>spirit,</hi> did at first frame so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a piece as man; and by cementing together two so contrary parts, could make such a <hi>compositum,</hi> as is but a clod of clay quickned with the breath of Life; a dead cole kindled by a Divine spark, and a lump of flesh animated by the spirit of God.</p>
            <p>And this was in truth so rare a composition, that the <hi>Anthropomorphites</hi> thought God himself to be for form
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119235:9"/> like to Man: and <hi>Aristotle</hi> himself call's man a <hi>Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cosme,</hi> or <hi>little world;</hi> and he that studiously travels o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Isle of Man,</hi> shall therein find as many wonders, as there be in the <hi>Macrocosme;</hi> and Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> saith more, <hi>Omni miraculo quod sit per hominem, majus mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculum est ipse homo.</hi> Run through all the Miracles that ever were wrought by Man, and you will meet with none to be compared with Man himself.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This transcendent excellency of our cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation should stir us up to magnifie our Maker: It is a kind of bruitishness in us to take no notice of our Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Dignity; yea he that is not highly affected with the rumination hereof, deserves not indeed to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a man; who should lift up his heart to heaven, as well as his head is lifted up; as Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> counsels us, <hi>Cum statu oris, &amp; corporis animum,</hi> Let thy bodily state teach thee to erect thy soul; and that thou mayest know God the better, study thy self. <hi>Gae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo descendit,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this very consideration that the <hi>body is one,</hi> should teach us christian Unity and concord. It was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> apology to <hi>Lot</hi> in the 13. chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> at the 8. verse, <hi>Let there be no strife between me and thee, for we are brethren;</hi> and how much more ought all we that are christians to live in Unity and godly love, seeing we are not onely brethren of the same Parents, God and his Church, but so many <hi>members</hi> of the same <hi>body?</hi> But of this more anon when I come to handle the Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; for the present I hasten from the bodies Unity, to speak somewhat of the plurality of <hi>members,</hi> which is the next thing considerable.</p>
            <p>It was the infinite sapience of the Creatour to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the <hi>body</hi> of Man with variety of <hi>members.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119235:10"/>
            <p>First, because variety of parts proportionably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'nd procure beauty.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for Necessities sake, because no <hi>one member,</hi> though never so excellent in the kind, is able to perform so many several offices as the <hi>body</hi> stands in need of.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, for strength, for look how many distinct parts there be in the <hi>body,</hi> so much the more ability there is, and sufficiency in time of need: which may be one principal reason why God hath given us two eyes, two ears, two hands, two feet, &amp;c. That so if any one should chance to fail of doing its Office, the other might happily supply the defect thereof.</p>
            <p>To which let me add that in the Original our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle saith not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>but</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body</hi> are not onely many in number, but of divers natures, and sundry fashions; that so each of them might be fit to discharge its proper Function. Consider (saith <hi>Tertullian de carne Christi</hi>) in the body of man, in some sort like to the body of the earth, <hi>mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culos ut glebas, ossa ut saxa, aspice nervorum tenaces con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexus, ut traduces radicum; ac venarum ramosos discur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,, ut ambages rivorum, &amp; lanugines, ut muscos; &amp; carnem, ut cespitem, &amp; ipsos medullarum in abdito the sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros, ut metalla carnis,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But leaving his nice speculations, the <hi>body</hi> is usually in Scripture described by two general notions, viz. <hi>of flesh and bones;</hi> as in the second chapter of <hi>Genesis</hi> at at the 23. verse, where <hi>Adam</hi> speaking of his wife, saith <hi>This now is bone of my bone, and flesh of my flesh.</hi> And our Saviour after his Resurrection from the dead, willing to convince his Disciples, that he had no phantasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, but a reall, Naturall <hi>body,</hi> bids them <hi>to handle
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119235:10"/> him, and see;</hi> for a Spirit (saith he) <hi>hath not flesh and bone,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now God hath in the frame of our <hi>bodies</hi> fitted <hi>flesh</hi> and <hi>bones</hi> together, that so we may have both strength and motion: and besides that, our bones teach us,</p>
            <p>First, to confess our sins, and to cry to God for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; <hi>for while I held my tongue, my bones consumed away,</hi> saith that lively pattern of Repentance, in the 32. <hi>Psalm</hi> at the 3. verse.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To trust in God alone, as the same Princely Prophet speaks in the 34. <hi>Psalm,</hi> at the 20. verse, <hi>for God keeps all our bones so that not one of them is broken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, To praise God, as the 35. <hi>Psalm</hi> at the 10 verse, <hi>All my bones shall say unto thee, O Lord, who is like unto thee?</hi> and some of the Rabbins have well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, that there be just as many precepts in the Law of God, as <hi>Anatomists</hi> say there be bones greater and smaller in the body of man. And when we look upon our <hi>flesh,</hi> we are thereby put in mind,</p>
            <p>First of our natural frailty, <hi>for all flesh is grasse,</hi> saith the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> in his 40. chapter, at the 6. verse; so that in a qualified sence, we are but so many Gras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers, especially when we idle away our time in truthlesse vanitie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Our <hi>flesh</hi> may teach us humanity each to other, since we are all so near akinn: This argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Abimelech</hi> used to the <hi>Sichemites,</hi> in the 9. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Judges,</hi> at the 2. verse, <hi>I am flesh of your flesh,</hi> and in the 11. Chapter of the first book of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> all <hi>Israel</hi> said to King <hi>David, behold thou art flesh of our flesh.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119235:11"/>
            <p>Thirdly, Our <hi>flesh</hi> may be our remembrancer of charity to the poor, as the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> enforces the motive; <hi>when thou seest the naked cover him, and hide not thy face from thine own flesh,</hi> poverty cuts not off connaturality,</p>
            <p>And (if in the next place) we descend to a more distinct consideration of the bodily <hi>members,</hi> we cannot but observe therein.</p>
            <p>First the Majesty of some parts, for most creatures stand in awe of Mans very look; and as Saint <hi>Ambros<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> notes, they serve Man, and by humane institution they are brought by degrees to put off their own nature: <hi>Obliviscuntur quod nata sunt, induunt quod jubentur.</hi> Some that are criticks in the holy Tongue, observe that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word for an <hi>Eye,</hi> comes of a root which signifies a <hi>Well,</hi> because it is both the bodies Looking-glasse, and sends forth water.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Philosopher</hi> calls the Eare, <hi>the sense of understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> saith, <hi>that it tastes words:</hi> It is the pallate of the soul. It is curiously framed, that by the reper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussion of the sound we may hear others speak, and that the sound may last the longer, it hath many meanders and concavities.</p>
            <p>The lips, teeth, and tongue, are instruments of Speech, by which we communicate our Notions each to other, as the Angels do only by intuition.</p>
            <p>Not to insist upon particulars: we have some <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> common to us with the bruits, and they have all the sences too; and in the acutenesse of each, some of them excell us; <hi>Nos aper auditu pracellit, aranea tactu, valour odoratu, linu visu, simia gustu.</hi> But in two things men do very much exceed and excel all sublunary crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; <hi>viz.</hi> By reason in the <hi>soul,</hi> and the hand in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119235:11"/>
               <hi>body:</hi> yea <hi>Anaxagorus</hi> upon a diligent inquiry into, and survey of the properties and motions in the hand, as it were in an extasie of admiration, concluded Man to be the wisest creature, because he hath hands; as if they were the Well-head of all intellectual and artificial Elegancies.</p>
            <p>And to the same effect <hi>Galen</hi> argues, that because Man is the wisest of the bodily creatures, therefore he hath hands given him, that as he is the most intelligent, so he might have fit Organs to express and explane his skill and knowledge: With these man tames fierce Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, sturdy Steeds, wilde Bears, subtle Foxes, <hi>&amp;c. Docentur ut parvuli, serviunt ut infirmi, verberantur ut timidi, corriguntur ut subditi, denique in mores transeunt nostros.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this excellency of our several <hi>members</hi> should make us both the more careful over them, and the more fearful to turn them into so many instruments of unrighteousnesse. <hi>I am fearfully and wonderfully made,</hi> saith the <hi>Psalmist,</hi> and <hi>that my soul knowes right well.</hi> And the more we know the excellency of our bodily <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> the lesse should we abuse them: for God did not put such beauty on thy <hi>body,</hi> that thou shouldst wallow like a Sow, in the myre of uncleanesse: He gave thee not so clear, quick and sharp eye-sight, to lust in look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon an Harlot: He gave thee not such tender and purged ears, to listen to evil communicatious which corrupt good manners: He gave thee not such a volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble and perswasive Tongue, to ly, and flatter, and swear and curse, and blaspheme with: He gave thee not such dexterous hands to be the instruments of Bribery and Sacriledge, Oppression and Extortion, Rapine and blood-shed: In a word, considering, saith
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119235:12"/> Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> that our <hi>bodies are Temples of the holy Ghost:</hi> O let us take good heed how we prophane and pollute them; and he gives this Reason, <hi>Eorum nos Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorum cultores, &amp; antistites sumus; serviamus illi, cujus esse jam caepimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then two sorts are peccant, and so to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</p>
            <p>The one is of such persons as abuse their <hi>members,</hi> by seeking to find out new and strange wayes to add more beauty to them, then God thought fit to put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; I mean all such as patch and paint their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, frizle, colour and powder their hair, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They transgresse <hi>Gods Ordinance,</hi> when they thus transform that which he formed otherwise; and they turn his <hi>Image</hi> (saith our Apostle) <hi>into the image of an Harlot;</hi> they are seldome better that use the <hi>Cyprian</hi> Arts: and they have just cause to fear that at the Day of judgement God will not know them, at least not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge such mutuatitious Forms to be his Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manship.</p>
            <p>The other sort to be reproved, are all such as defile their <hi>bodies,</hi> and deform themselves by any vitious qualities; as by luxury, which our Apostle calls sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing against our own <hi>body;</hi> or by lazinesse, which the wise man call'd <hi>A living mans Sepulture;</hi> or by surfeiting, which hath destroyed more then Sword, Pestilence and Famine; or by Envy; For an envious Man counts an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others good his hurt: <hi>parum est si ipse sit foelix, nisi al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sit infoelix.</hi> And therefore <hi>Bonaventure</hi> in his <hi>Diet of Health,</hi> wittily compares each envious wretch to <hi>Cain,</hi> who said of himself in the 4. of <hi>Gen. Whosoever findes ma, shall slay me:</hi> For in all that he meets with he either sees that which is good, and then he repines;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119235:12"/> or that which is evil, and then he rejoyces; and both these slay the envious: Or by anger, in which his hair stands on end, to shew the obdurate inflexiblenesse of his mind, his eyes stare and kindle, as if with the <hi>Cockatrice</hi> or <hi>Basilisk,</hi> he would kill with a look, he grates and gnashes his teeth, as if he would grind all to powder; his Face is now red and anone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ale, as if it either blush'd for shame of the minds Folly, or envied others Good, his Tongue fumbles and faulters, as not being able to expresse the rage of his heart, his blood boyles ready to burst through the veins, as if it were afraid to make longer stay in so furious a body; his brest swells, as if it were not large enough to contain the passion; his hands and feet tremble and beat each against other, as if the little world were in an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, which threatens nothing but desolation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. Our Apostle in the 15 ch. of the 1. Epistle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> saith <hi>that he had fought with Beasts, after the manner of men</hi> which Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> expounds <hi>of brutish Men,</hi> such as kick backward like Asses, raven like Wolves, roame like Boares, grin like Dogs, neigh like Horses, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Men in shape, these and such like Beasts in conditions. Beasts, did I say! Saint <hi>Ambrose</hi> saith, that they are worse then beasts, <hi>Nam omni Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stia bestialior est Homo, rationem habens, &amp; non secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum rationem vivens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I have shewed both that the <hi>body</hi> is <hi>one,</hi> and also that in the Unity of the <hi>body</hi> there is a plurality of <hi>members:</hi> It now onely remains that I touch in a word, that those many <hi>members</hi> in this <hi>one body</hi> have not the same <hi>Office:</hi> which is the last thing considerable in the first main part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The eye to see, and the eare to hear</hi> saith <hi>Solomon</hi> in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119235:13"/> 20. Chapter of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> at the 12. verse, <hi>One God is the maker of them both.</hi> As if he had said, God hath imprinted in each <hi>member</hi> his proper Faculty, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it his <hi>office,</hi> as our Apostle demonstrates at large in the 12. chapter of the first Epistle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> where we read that <hi>the eye cannot say to the hand, I have no need of thee; nor the head to the foot, I have no need of thee;</hi> neither doth any one <hi>member</hi> in the <hi>body,</hi> encroach upon the <hi>office</hi> of an other: and thence flowes that sweet Harmony in the <hi>body;</hi> in which as in a perfect consort, every instrument being exactly tuned, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs to make up the consent of the whole. Thus the <hi>eye</hi> (which our Saviour calls <hi>the light of the body</hi>) sees for the feet; and the feet walk for the hands, and the hands work for the mouth, and the mouth feeds for the stomach, and the stomach disgests for the belly, and the belly is the draught or sinck to carry away the Excrements of the whole <hi>body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which teacheth us,</p>
            <p>First, to be modest, and like the <hi>bodily members</hi> not to usurp anothers <hi>office.</hi> It is a foul fault in these dayes that some will not onely be judging and censuring o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in such things as they doe little understand, or grant they did, yet they do not at all concern them; but also that they will be intermedling in other mens matters, and they will enterfere in other mens callings, they will, as the Proverb is, be busie Bishops in other mens Diocesse; and think nothing well done, unlesse they have an hand in doing it: but this fault would soon be amended, would they but considerately observe the carriage of their own <hi>bodily members;</hi> among which they cannot but take notice, that the eye doth not controwle the eare, nor the feet the hands, but each
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119235:13"/> doth its proper duty according to its place: and this tacitely implyes, that if thou be an hearer, 'tis presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to speak in the Congregation; and if thou be a Subject, thou maist not prescribe Lawes: <hi>Quis te constituit Judicem?</hi> said the <hi>Sodomites</hi> to <hi>Lot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, we are taught hence both to praise God for the sound <hi>members of our own bodies,</hi> and also for the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some <hi>members of the body politick,</hi> as it takes in both Church and State, which have long languished under a deep &amp; dangerous distemper and disorder (as the crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did at the pool of <hi>Bethesda</hi>) for want of a Man: but now God be thanked we have a Man like <hi>David</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods own heart, he hath restored our Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraign unto us; and together with and under him, such Magistrates and Ministers, as like so many conduict-pipes may conveigh unto us our old good Lawes and Religion, and establish us in our just Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Properties?</p>
            <p>The Heathen Oratour notes, that it is no small com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to any man, when he hath all his sences sound and vigorous; <hi>Mentem sanam in corpore sano.</hi> Then much more comfort must it needs be to us, to see all the <hi>members of the body politick</hi> now apt and able to do their respective duties: wherefore let us who are in the state of Grace; observe and imitate the <hi>bodily members</hi> in the state of Nature: I say let the <hi>natural body</hi> thus far teach the <hi>body mysticall:</hi> For this I take to be the chief scope, and drift of our Apostle in his Reddition: So we being many, are <hi>one body in Christ,</hi> and each of us <hi>members one of another;</hi> which words contain the second main part of my Text.</p>
            <p>And the first thing in this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that offers it self to our consideration, Is the Unity <hi>of Christs body mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:119235:14"/> in some sort proportionable to that of the <hi>body na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural;</hi> For that in the former verse is but <hi>One body,</hi> and <hi>We are one body in Christ,</hi> saith the Apostle here; and herein he shewes <hi>both the Unity of the Church;</hi> in that he calls it <hi>one body;</hi> and also the Author of the same; <hi>viz.</hi> Christ, <hi>we are one body in Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the former, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Churches Unity</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed here, when our Apostle calls it, <hi>one body.</hi> Now that all the Faithful make but <hi>one Church,</hi> as all the <hi>Members do but one body,</hi> may be evinc'd out of the sixt Chapter of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> at the 8. Verse; where though we find mention made <hi>of threescore Queens and Virgins without number,</hi> (Christs <hi>mystical members</hi> being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to Queens for Majesty, and for Purity to Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins) yet the Church it self, (which the Spouse there styles <hi>his Dove, his undefiled</hi>) is but <hi>one;</hi> yea, she is <hi>the onely one of her Mother, the choice one of her that bare her:</hi> Or as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> renders it, <hi>Ecclesia non solum una, sed &amp; unica; vel, si ità loqui liceat, unissima:</hi> For so she is in divers respects, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First in regard of one and the same Original; for one and the same God, hath both call'd and chosen his Church, <hi>Who is yesterday, and to day, and the same for ever,</hi> as our Apostle speaks.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in regard of one and the same end, Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which is alike common <hi>to all the members of the true Church;</hi> For so saith Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in the first Chapter of his first Epistle General, at the ninth verse, <hi>Receiving the end of your Faith, even the salvation of your Soules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in regard the means are the same to bring them all to this one end; for the same Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; the same Faith and Obedience; the same
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119235:14"/> Regeneration, and Repentance, are propounded to all alike.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, in regard of the same Spirit; for by <hi>one</hi> Spirit (which <hi>Tertullian</hi> fitly styles, <hi>Vicarium Christi,</hi> Christs Vicar generall upon Earth) his Church is animated, ordered and governed all the World over.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, in regard of <hi>one head;</hi> For all true believers receive the same influence of Grace, from Christ <hi>their Head;</hi> whence it distils upon all and every of his <hi>mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal members,</hi> as <hi>the Oyle that was powred on the head of</hi> Aaron, <hi>ran down to the very skirts of his cloathing,</hi> in the 133. <hi>Psalm,</hi> at the 2. verse.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, in regard of the strict connexion between this <hi>one head,</hi> and all the <hi>members;</hi> for by one and the same bond of peace, and Christian love, the faithful are tied each to other; all to Christ.</p>
            <p>Here then you see,</p>
            <p>First what an happy and blessed thing it is for all Christians to live in Unity and godly Love; which the sweet singer of <hi>Israel</hi> displayes with an <hi>En &amp; eccè</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Behold how good and pleasant a thing it is for brethren to dwell together in Unity?</hi> And therein he insinuates, that it contains in it all kinds of good; as being both honest, and pleasant, and profitable: And upon this ground Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> cries out, <hi>Unum cogitate fratres, &amp; videte in ipsa multitudine si delectat nisi unum? Ecce Deo propitio, quam multi estis! Quis vos ferret nisi unum saperetis! Unde in multis ista quies? Da unum populus est, tolle unum, turba est: quid enim est turba, nisi multitudo turbata?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the next place, <hi>this Unity of the body naturall,</hi> applyed to the Church, which is <hi>Christs Body mystical,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119235:15"/> should teach us especially to avoid three things, as <hi>threatning danger,</hi> if not <hi>destruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The first whereof is <hi>Curiosity;</hi> for as in the <hi>body</hi> when <hi>one member</hi> busies it self in the <hi>Office</hi> of another: so in the Church, when men will needs be intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in matters that they have nothing to do with; it must needs disturb the welfare of the whole. It is not for Mechaniques to enterfare on the Magistrates or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters duty nor may they think themselves, fit, able and worthy, to discharge their places. They shall do well to call to mind how dear it cost <hi>Cora, Dathan, Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, Uzzah</hi> and others, for taking too much upon them in this kind. I would have one that is thus over-wise to tell me; if a Mote should chance to fall into the eye, and the foot should strive to prevent the hand in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking to take it out, whether that would not be a rude part, and perform'd with as ill successe? And if he cannot rationally deny that, then he must needs grant me this; that every one ought to keep himself within the lists and precincts of his proper Calling; least if they stand to justifie such usurpation and intrusion; they turn <hi>Sion</hi> into <hi>Babylon;</hi> and both Church and State into a Chaos of confusion.</p>
            <p>The second is <hi>Arrogancy;</hi> for as <hi>one member of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> doth not insult over an other: so if thou be prefer'd in the Church, thou must not look like a son of <hi>Anak</hi> upon others as so many Grashoppers. While fools admire thy promotion, all wisemen examine thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and thy parts too, they seldome honour any thing, but merit. <hi>Mardocai</hi> did not buckle to <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> himself in the ruffe of his pride; because though he was the Courts Favourite, yet he was the Churches Enemy: neither could <hi>Haman</hi> more undervalue <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docai</hi>'s
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119235:15"/> outward meanness, then <hi>Mardocai</hi> did <hi>Hamans</hi> inward emptinesse. Then let no man look and speak bigg; for the feet that dayly trudge through thick and thinn; are as needful as the head that is so lofty; and were it not for the legs and feet that support it, the head must needs tumble in the dirt. All the <hi>members of the body</hi> are quickned alike with the same soul: <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia diversa</hi> (saith Saint <hi>Augustine) vita communis.</hi> And thus it is in the Church of Christ; in which whilest e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man keeps his own station, and acts his own part; the benefit redounds to the common good. Then over-ween not thy self, undervalue not others; for take away Peasants, and what will become of Potentates? Who sees not that the rich stands in as much need of the poor mans service, as the poorest wretch alive doth of the rich mans salary?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This Doctrine of Unity in the Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns the monstrous sin of Schisme: Christ will have his <hi>mystical body One;</hi> and wilt thou needs divide it into parts? The common Souldiers, though barbarous, would not divide Christ's Coat because <hi>it was seamlesse;</hi> and darest thou divide his Church, which is <hi>One and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly One?</hi> It must needs be a misgrounded and misguided zeal (though varnish'd with the pretence of Religion and Reformation) which stirs thee up, and pricks thee on to do that which ordinary reaso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would not permit the Souldiers themselves to do; <hi>viz.</hi> to divide that which is <hi>seamlesse;</hi> and by cutting it into parts to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the whole. <hi>Tantum Religio potuit suadere malorum.</hi> This Schisme is spawn'd by the Devil himself: (whom our Saviour styles <hi>the envious man;</hi> Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> calls him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a counselling enemy; and St. <hi>John</hi> names him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>A destroyer,</hi> he begets Schism
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119235:16"/> between pride and hatred: Schisme commonly begins in pride; for by pride alone Man makes contention, saith <hi>Solomon</hi> in the 13. Chapter of the <hi>Pr verbs,</hi> at the 10. verse: and the Scismatiques pride is the worst in the kind, <hi>viz.</hi> Spiritual pride, <hi>Luciferian</hi> pride; <hi>I will be like the most High,</hi> said <hi>Lucifer</hi> in the 14. Chapter of <hi>Isaiah;</hi> and thereby he did what he could to make a Schisme in Heaven, and it is generally true of Scisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques on Earth, what Saint <hi>Ambrose</hi> reports of <hi>Novatus</hi> the Heretick; <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Episcopatus amissi dolore suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>census Schisma composuit;</hi> he affecting a Bishoprick, and seeing a worthier then himself prefer'd unto it, caused a Schisme in the Church. And we have had some am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious and turbulent spirits, who when for want of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, they could not become equal to the Bishops in Ecclesiastical Dignity, they made it their work (as <hi>Aerius</hi> did) to pull down the Bishops, and to level the Church, by an <hi>Anabaptistical</hi> party. They cried down Prelacy, and Lording it over the Flock; but pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equality, they sought Dominion. Thus we now plainly discover that the late Schisme took the first rise from pride and avarice; and it will end, as it hath hitherto gone on, in envy, hatred, malice, and all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitablenesse.</p>
            <p>And as the <hi>members of the body</hi> natural cannot endure a Schisme among <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>emselves: so neither doe they se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate each from other: which Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> (speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of himself, and all other <hi>members of Christs Church</hi>) applies and illustrates thus; <hi>Neque enim,</hi> &amp;c. Neither for the Tares doe we leave God's Field; nor for the Chaffe, his Floor; nor for the Goats, doe we leave his Fold; nor for the Vessels of dishonour do we forsake his house, the Church; which our Apostle calls the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119235:16"/> and Ground of Truth, And Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> upon the parable of the <hi>Virgins</hi> (in the 25. chapter of Saint <hi>Matthew</hi>) well and wittily observes that all men what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever are denoted and comprehended in and under those <hi>ten Virgins,</hi> as being either <hi>wise or foolish:</hi> and if they be <hi>foolish,</hi> they stand in need of the <hi>wise;</hi> but if they be <hi>wise,</hi> then the <hi>foolish</hi> stand in need of them so that whether they be <hi>wise</hi> or <hi>foolish,</hi> yet they may not separate themselves: This Doctrine we learn from the <hi>members of the body;</hi> for if the head ake, doth the foot therefore refuse to bear it? Or if the eye be blemi'sht do the other <hi>members</hi> forsake it? Nay rather do not all the rest do their best endeavour to cherish it? what then doe all Separatists get by their gathering of Churches, or creeping into corners, and crumbling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to peculiar Congregations; but onely to cut off them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from all hope and expectation of life and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from Christ, who is the <hi>Head of the Church?</hi> Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> enforceth it thus, <hi>Sicut enim,</hi> &amp;c. For as a <hi>member</hi> that is rent from a living <hi>body,</hi> cannot possibly retain life in it: so whosoever departs from <hi>the Unity of the Church,</hi> he cannot participate of the Spirit of Life and Grace, which animates and regulates the same.</p>
            <p>But the Popes Janizaries, the Jesuits, (who have been active in our late troubles) lay the same imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon us, who are the profest <hi>members</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> which we doe upon our brethren (that we justly call Separatists) for they call us Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiques, because we are fallen from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which had formerly been our Mother? and which (say they) is <hi>the Mother Church</hi> and <hi>the true Vine?</hi> and they hold that it is at this day <hi>De necessitate salutis,</hi> to be Subject to the Pope? and they add withal that all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119235:17"/> our late distortions and distractions, are Gods just judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon us for our former Schisme and separation from them?</p>
            <p>The charge I confesse is heavy; but the comfort is our answer is easie and ready:</p>
            <p>For first we say, and are able to prove that it is not we that have departed from the Unity both of <hi>Verity</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> but they: for they have long since for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken the holy ancient Doctrine; and set abroach ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny new points of Religion, which in the <hi>Tridentine</hi> Council are made so many Articles of Faith; some of which were scarce heard of, much lesse universally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieved in the Primitive Church; not many hundred years after.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We wholly deny that there is any abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute necessity, that all Christians should be subject to the Pope: we know that the <hi>Greek Church</hi> never was, and they must acknowledge that a great part of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome</hi> at this day is not; and in plain <hi>English</hi> may not keep communion with the Papacy; which not a few of the most Orthodox Divines have from time to time held to be mystical <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, We are ready to prove that we have not forsaken the ancient Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> (many of whose Bishops lived and died Professors, Confessors and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs for the cause of Christ) but onely the new fangled Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> pride, the <hi>Roman</hi> supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the <hi>Roman</hi> errours and absurdities, I had almost said the <hi>Romish Antichrist;</hi> with whom we have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and may have no more to do; save to justfie our separation, we being in very deed no farther departed from her, then she is from her self.</p>
            <p>And therefore we are confident (that God who in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119235:17"/> mercy did at first open our eyes to see, and our hearts to loath the <hi>Romish</hi> impostures, and abominations) hath not laid upon us these divisions among our selves, as his judgement for our defection from the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> but rather for our great unthankfulnesse to him, who call'd us out of so grosse darknesse, into this mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous light; and for our unworthinesse of the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous means of Grace, Peace and Truth, which above all the neighbouring Nations, we so long and happily enjoyed, and yet so horribly abused by our late inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations and wilful rising up against all that is called God among us; and have not yet soundly repented for the same.</p>
            <p>And thus having shewed that the <hi>body</hi> of the Church is but <hi>one;</hi> I hasten now to speak somewhat of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Unity, <hi>viz.</hi> Christ; for as the Church is <hi>one body,</hi> so it is <hi>one body</hi> in Christ, saith our Apostle; which is the second particular in the first part of the Reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>As the Church is <hi>one body,</hi> so it must be the Church christian, or it cannot be <hi>one body</hi> in Christ; for Christ is the Head of it, and it is coupled together in, by, and under him. This <hi>body</hi> of the Church Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian) began in the twelve Apostles, who were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and chosen immediately by Christ himself; and he gave them a speciall Commission to preach the <hi>Gospel to all Nations,</hi> in the 28. chapter of Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> and by their Ministry the Church was propagated, and dispersed over the face of the Earth: but wheresoever the <hi>members</hi> were planted, yet still they made up but <hi>one body</hi> in Christ, all the lines of the Churches circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference still terminated in him alone as their centre; as our Apostle demonstrates (in the 4. chapter to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119235:18"/>
               <hi>Ephesians,</hi> at the 15. verse) how all the <hi>members</hi> of the Church are coupled together in Christ, who is the Head from whence the whole <hi>body,</hi> being knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as with so many joynts, receives all it's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence.</p>
            <p>Then the Church is neither without an Head; as the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> fancy a Church like a Spider, or <hi>Plinies Acephali,</hi> all body and no head: Neither is it all head and no body, as the <hi>Papists</hi> have framed a Church like a Toad-stool, For <hi>Harveus</hi> makes the Catholick Church to be nothing but the present <hi>Roman</hi> Church; and most of that perswasion hold the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be nothing but the <hi>Pope;</hi> who (say they) is virtually the whole Church; <hi>Admiranda canant, sed non cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For if <hi>Cardinals</hi> and <hi>Jesuites</hi> be justly reputed Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, as being men of all Professions, Orders, Degrees, Offices and Benefices: then I leave them to judge what a Monster of Monsters the <hi>Pope</hi> must needs be, seeing they believe him to be all these; and yet they must confesse that none of these can be both the head and the bodie too.</p>
            <p>Neither is the Church double-headed; Christ one Head, and the Pope another as <hi>Hart</hi> the <hi>Jesuite</hi> (out of his Master <hi>Stapleton</hi>) nicely distinguishes them thus: The <hi>Church</hi> hath <hi>one Head, viz. Christ</hi> who is properly <hi>the Head of the Church,</hi> principal, invisible, and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and the <hi>Pope</hi> (saith he) is the other <hi>Head,</hi> impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, visibly and Ministerially; not to enliven, but to direct the <hi>body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he must know and acknowledge, that the <hi>Office</hi> of Direction is only proper to the <hi>Head</hi> that quickens; and that is <hi>Christ</hi> alone, who as the <hi>Head of the Church,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119235:18"/> hath promised to be with it for Direction to the end of the world: That so as <hi>one body</hi> sanctified by <hi>one Spirit,</hi> through the <hi>Sacrament of one Baptisme,</hi> knit to <hi>Christ in one Faith,</hi> and to each other <hi>in one Bond of Love,</hi> it should serve <hi>one Lord,</hi> under <hi>one hope of Eternal Life.</hi> So that <hi>Christ</hi> alone is the <hi>adequate Head of this body,</hi> He holds good proportion with the whole <hi>body,</hi> which the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot possibly do.</p>
            <p>And should we admit, what the <hi>Romish</hi> sticklers so eagerly contend for, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>the Pope is Head of the Church;</hi> then they cannot deny but sometimes the <hi>Church</hi> hath had a <hi>She-head,</hi> as <hi>Pope Joane;</hi> and that the <hi>Church</hi> hath sometimes had no <hi>Head</hi> at all, for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of <hi>Euaristus</hi> there was no <hi>Pope</hi> for thirty eight years, eight moneths, and some odd dayes, as their own <hi>Chronicles</hi> record; and that there were a while three <hi>Popes</hi> at once; and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himself in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniously confesseth, that no man could certainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, which of the three was the right Pope: seeing that each of them had many learned men to defend him; during all which time <hi>the Church of Rome</hi> was like <hi>Cerberus</hi> a Monster of three heads: whereas the <hi>Church Catholick</hi> as it is <hi>one body</hi> in the Text, so is it <hi>one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in Christ,</hi> saith our Apostle: so that in truth no more have <hi>Christ for their Head,</hi> then onely they that are sound and living <hi>members</hi> of this <hi>one body</hi> in the Text. The <hi>Lord Christ</hi> (saith Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>) is <hi>a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of coelestial Spices, and a Fountain of spiritual Graces, both to the whole body of his Church, and also to every living member of the same.</hi> And therefore as the Princely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> chears himself in the 23. <hi>Psalm,</hi> that <hi>the Lord is his Shepheard,</hi> and therefore he can lack nothing: so much more may all the true <hi>members of this mystical
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119235:19"/> body</hi> comfort themselves with this consideration, that the <hi>Lord Christ is their Head,</hi> and therefore they can lack nothing: And since he is our <hi>Head,</hi> who in the 14 chapter of Saint <hi>John</hi> at the 6. verse) <hi>Is the way, and the Truth, and the Life;</hi> We that are <hi>his mystical members,</hi> may be in some good measure assured, that he condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting us we cannot possibly wander out of the way; totally fall from the Truth, and finally fail of Life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting. And thus you have seen the parallel of the first main part of this comparison, in which I have done my endeavour to prove and clear two things, <hi>viz.</hi> both that the whole <hi>Church</hi> is but <hi>one body;</hi> and also that it is <hi>one Body in Christ;</hi> He is the onely <hi>Head of it.</hi> The next thing remarkable in this Reddition here, is that this <hi>one body of the Church</hi> hath many <hi>members:</hi> for so stands the words, <hi>So we being many, are one body,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>the body of Christs Church be one,</hi> yet are the <hi>members</hi> thereof many: for our Saviour saith, in the 20. chapter of Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> at the 16. verse, <hi>Many are called, but few are chosen:</hi> and look how many are called, so many be the <hi>members of the visible Church;</hi> for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward calling and profession, make men <hi>members of the Church.</hi> And in the 10. chapter to the <hi>Romans</hi> at the 18. verse, Our Apostle (speaking of the Apostles and Disciples sent to preach the Gospel) saith <hi>Their sound is gone out into all the world:</hi> That sound was the signal to call them; and when the sound is so universally diffus'd, as throughout the Universe, the persons call'd must needs be many.</p>
            <p>And though our Saviour saith there, That <hi>but few are chosen;</hi> He doth not mean that the Elect are but few in themselves, but that they are few in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of them that are call'd; as you may see in divers
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119235:19"/> Learned and Laborious men, who have professedly handled the argument of <hi>Christianographie;</hi> in which they have made a clear Discovery, that <hi>Christianity</hi> is now planted and propagated in most parts of the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table world.</p>
            <p>So that if we seriously consider the <hi>Church</hi> in it self, it must be acknowledged to be a <hi>Body</hi> collected and compacted of all Nations; and consequently the <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> thereof must needs be exceeding many; and upon this ground we professe in the Apostles Creed, <hi>That we believe the holy Catholick Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let me tell you that it is both the <hi>Churches</hi> Beauty, Strength and Glory, that in her <hi>members</hi> she is dispersed far and wide over the face of the Earth; in which regard the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Greek</hi> is stil'd <hi>Catholick;</hi> that is, <hi>Universal;</hi> and so she is no lesse truly, then properly stil'd in many respects, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, in respect of place; for the <hi>Church Christian</hi> is not confin'd to one Nation as was that of the <hi>Jewes;</hi> but it extends to all Nations. I say it is not restring d either to <hi>Africk,</hi> or <hi>Rome, Amsterdam, Geneva,</hi> or <hi>New-England,</hi> much lesse to any gathered <hi>Church,</hi> peculiar Congregation, or corner-creeping Conventicle. But it is extended to all places; For God saith to Christ in the 2. <hi>Psalm</hi> at the 8. verse, <hi>I will give thee the Heathen for thine inheritance, and the uttermost parts of the Earth for thy possession.</hi> And Saint <hi>John</hi> in the 7. chapter of the <hi>Revelation</hi> at the 9. verse, saith, <hi>And I beheld, and loe, a great multitude which no man could number of all Nations and Kindreds, and People, and Languages stood before the Throne, and before the Lamb, cloath'd with white Robes, and with Palmes in their hands▪</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Those <hi>white Robes,</hi> signified their Purity; those
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119235:20"/>
               <hi>Palmes,</hi> their Victory; and their standing before the <hi>Lamb,</hi> their Glory; which among other considerations, moved <hi>Bellarmine</hi> to write that no lesse comfortable, then admirable Treatise, <hi>De amplitudine regni coelestis.</hi> But the <hi>Church triumphant</hi> could not be of that ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude he speaks of, were not the <hi>members</hi> of the <hi>Church militant</hi> exceeding many as Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> insinuates when he saith, <hi>Ecclesia expassis sinibus,</hi> &amp;c. The Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some and Armes of the <hi>Church</hi> are open to embrace all Nations. And Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> saith, <hi>Ecclesia dicitur Catholica,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Church</hi> is called <hi>Catholick,</hi> because it is diffused throughout the world. Thus <hi>Catholick</hi> is the <hi>Church</hi> in regard of place, and consequently the <hi>members</hi> thereof are many.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Church</hi> is called <hi>Catholick</hi> in regard it takes in men of all qualities and conditions; <hi>genera sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulorum</hi> (as the School speaks) though not <hi>singula gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> Gods <hi>Church</hi> is made up of all sorts of people, high and low, rich and poor, bond and free, wise and simple, learned and ignorant, noble, and ignoble, one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. For God would have all men to be saved, in the second chapter of the first Epistle to <hi>Timothy</hi> at the 4. verse. And for this cause at the first verse, of the same Chapter, our Apostle exhorts <hi>that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and supplications, and Intercessions be made for all men in general, and especially for Kings,</hi> &amp;c. And we have in Scripture examples of all sorts, as of <hi>Abraham</hi> among the <hi>Canaanites, Joseph</hi> among the <hi>Aegyptians, Iob</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Idumaans, Daniel,</hi> among the <hi>Idolaters, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tathias</hi> among the <hi>Apostata's, Nicodemus</hi> among the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risees, Joseph of Arimathea</hi> among the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> among the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Thus (as the Apostle speaks in the 10. chapter of the <hi>Acts</hi> at the 34. verse) you may
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119235:20"/> perceive <hi>that God is no respecter of persons;</hi> but in every Nation he that fears God and works righteousn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sse, is accepted of him: and Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> adds, <hi>Qui seipsum excipit, seipsum decipit:</hi> He that excepts himself, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives himself; he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat doth his duty may expect Gods blessing; as God himself inculcated to <hi>Cain</hi> in the 4. chap. of <hi>Gen. If thou dost well, shalt thou not be accepted?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It was therefore a presumptuous errour in the <hi>Iewes</hi> to plead (as they did in the 3. chapter of Saint <hi>Matthew) We have Abraham to our Father;</hi> as if the grace of God had been intail'd upon them for ever; For our Apostle proves that intayl to be cut off long agoe, and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition wall to be broken down, and that in the <hi>body of Christs Church</hi> the former nice differences of <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> bond and free, male and female are taken away, and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in his vision of a sheet let down from Heaven (in which all sorts of creatures were promis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuously exposed both to his eye and his appetite) was tacitely taught that what God hath sanctified, no man should dare to think, or call common and unclean: and consequently the <hi>members</hi> of the Church are many, in respect it takes in some of all sorts and conditions.</p>
            <p>Thirdly the <hi>Church</hi> is <hi>Catholick,</hi> in regard it extends to all parts of time; <hi>viz.</hi> past, present and future; for it began with the beginning of time, and shall continue till time shall be no more. For as Christ, who <hi>is the Head of the Church, is yesterday, and to day, and the same for ever;</hi> so is his mystical <hi>body</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> too: when this fails the world cannot stand; For the <hi>members</hi> thereof are the props and pillars of it; as the Prophet <hi>Elizeus</hi> cried out to <hi>Elias</hi> at his translation, <hi>My Father, my Father, the chariots of Israel, and the Horsemen of the same?</hi> The strength of <hi>Israel</hi> consists in these: No
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119235:21"/> chariots and horsemen can so safe guard any place, as the Saints do their persons among whom they live. In plagues, in dearths and other calamities, it lies no doubt in the powerful prayers of some few the Friends and Favourites of God to avert the judgement, and to make an attonement for the wicked among whom they live, as the Scripture shewes in <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Noah, Lot, Iob, Daniel,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Church Militant</hi> is the <hi>Nursery</hi> to the <hi>Church Triumphant;</hi> and it is true in this, which is observed in all other <hi>Nurseries;</hi> still some embrio's in the Faith, as so many tender plants are inserted, inoculated and ingrafted into the <hi>mystical Vine,</hi> as others are dayly transplanted thence from <hi>Grace</hi> to <hi>Glory.</hi> And conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the <hi>members</hi> thereof are many.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the <hi>Church</hi> is also <hi>Catholick</hi> in regard of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> for the <hi>Faith</hi> is one and the same among all Nations; as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> speaks, <hi>Omnium credentium Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des una.</hi> All the sincere <hi>members</hi> of Christs <hi>Church</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially embrace, and orally professe the whole and sole Doctrine of the Prophets and Apostles, upon whom they are built, <hi>Christ himself being the chief corner stone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There may be some difference in Ceremonies, (and it is wished there were lesse among us, who can neither have fewer, unlesse we would have the body of the <hi>Church</hi> stark naked; nor yet more innocent and inoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive then those which are retain'd in the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whose Piety and Prudence it was in the Infancy of Reformation, to keep the golden mean between Popish Superstition, and Phanatical profanenesse; and therefore it is sin and pity, that some out of Pride, prejudice or Interest, wilfully break the Churches U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, rather then meekly submit to the Supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119235:21"/> by which they are establish'd) but sure I am the substantial part is ever the same: For the Articles of Faith can neither encrease, notwithstanding the super-institution of the Tridentive Council; nor yet decrease, notwithstanding the late brain-sick fury of some Zelots pretending to Reformation, which for the time rejected the three Creeds, which have been ever receiv'd by the whole <hi>Christian Church:</hi> Neither doe the Articles change or alter in any Fundamentals, against which we have a sure promise, <hi>That the gates of Hell</hi> it self <hi>shall never prevail.</hi> And this serves for the just conviction both of <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Phanaticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, I say it discovers the absurdity, and so stops the mouths of all such as usually stile themselves <hi>Roman-Caholicks:</hi> I have shewed already that the <hi>Church of Christ</hi> is call'd <hi>Catholick,</hi> because it extends to all places, times, &amp;c. but the present <hi>Roman Church</hi> is but of ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterday in comparison; and at most but a National Church, and that none of the best neither; but grant it were better then in truth it is, yet (as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> speaks) <hi>Orbis major esturbe.</hi> And that onely is <hi>Catholick,</hi> saith <hi>Vincentius Lyrinensis,</hi> not which some few <hi>(sed quod omnes pariter uno; eodemque consensu, aperte, frequenter, &amp; perseveranter tenuerunt)</hi> but which all alike have with one and the same consent, publickly, frequently and perseveringly held; and this no more agrees to <hi>Popery,</hi> then to <hi>Judaisme;</hi> for the <hi>Trent</hi> Faith was not known many hundred years after Christ.</p>
            <p>And it also convinces all Phanaticks, whose Faith and Churches are particular; whereas the Apostle as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert's, that no Scripture is of private Interpretation; and the ring-leaders of these peculiar Congregations, either through ignorance, or affectation, falling short of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119235:22"/>
               <hi>Catholick</hi> sence and interpretation of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, can never approve themselves and their follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, so many sound <hi>members</hi> of the holy <hi>Catholick Church.</hi> And therefore what <hi>Tertullian</hi> speaks of the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cionites,</hi> I may apply to all other Hereticks and Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks; <hi>faciunt favos &amp; vespae, faciunt Ecclesias &amp; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionitae.</hi> These make <hi>Churches,</hi> as the Wasps doe make combes; For as Wasps have no good Hony in their Combes, but live onely upon robbing of the Bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hives: so all Separatists have little or none of the Scripture Truth among them, which the <hi>Psalmist</hi> saith is sweeter then Hony and the Hony-comb: but they live and thrive by the sacrilegious ruines of the <hi>Church:</hi> and as the same <hi>Tertullian</hi> speaks, <hi>Nostra suffodiunt, ut sua aedificent.</hi> They build up their <hi>Babels</hi> with the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of <hi>Sion;</hi> and with <hi>Micah</hi> their good Master, they care not how much they rend and tear the <hi>Churches</hi> Garments, so their own may be whole.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As this Doctrine sets forth both the beauty and comelynesse of <hi>Christs mystical body;</hi> that the <hi>members</hi> thereof are many: so doth it exceedingly commend the incomprehensible wisedome and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of God, in ordering his Church so sweetly; that men born, and living never so far asunder, and differing very much each from other in customes, manners and languages; yet agree so well together in the <hi>verity of Christian Religion,</hi> and <hi>unity of the Catholick Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for this among other Reasons, I conceive that <hi>Christs Church</hi> in the 6. chapter of the <hi>Canticles</hi> at the 4. ver. is compared to <hi>an Army with Banners.</hi> For as it is observable in an army, that some carry these colours, others those; some march under this Chieftain, others under that; some are Horse-men, others Foot-men, &amp;c.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119235:22"/> yet all concur to make up the beauty and strength of the whole Army, which hath but one and the same dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, under one General or Commander in chief: Even so it is in the Church; For Almighty God hath one Regiment among us, another in <hi>Holland,</hi> a third in <hi>France,</hi> a fourth in <hi>Germany,</hi> &amp;c. For our Apostle saith in his Reddition here, that we are many <hi>Members:</hi> and yet admit them to be nere so many, it is note-worthy in the Text, that all these taken collectively, make but <hi>one body in Christ:</hi> and so should all live under one Discipline.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this should improve our Charity and Hos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality towards exiles and strangers; seeing that they professing Christianity, be <hi>members</hi> with us <hi>of one and the same mystical body,</hi> Souldiers of the same Army, Trees of the same Orchard, Branches of the same Vine, Corn of the same Field, Sheep of the same Fold, &amp;c. Let us not then be envious and malicious, but harbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and helpful each to other: Let not any difference in Opinions cause distance in our affections; but let us joyntly and severally pray <hi>for the peace of Jerusalem;</hi> and let us all make a conscience of practising what we pretend to pray for by endeavouring to keep <hi>the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of peace.</hi> And since the evil an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels conspire together for the propagating and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of Sathans kingdome: Oh let not any of us either by open schisme, or private separation discerp and tear in pieces the <hi>Church</hi> which is <hi>Christs Kingdome;</hi> and though we be many in number, yet let us be <hi>as one man in judgement;</hi> at least let us not highten our differences to the losse of Christian concord; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let us agree like Brethren; and which is yet nearer like <hi>members</hi> of the same body for the compleating
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119235:23"/> of the beauty and safety of the whole.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Though the <hi>Church militant</hi> be not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether so vast as the Church malignant, yet let not this paucity discourage any man from being <hi>one of Christ's little flock,</hi> as it did <hi>Rutholdus</hi> Duke of <hi>Fridland,</hi> who when he had one foot in the water ready to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd, demanded of the Priest who was to Officiate, <hi>An plures,</hi> &amp;c. Whether he thought that more of his progenitours were saved or damned? as having lived and dyed <hi>out of the communion of the Church;</hi> and the Priest replying, that <hi>extra Ecclesiam non est salus:</hi> the Duke thereupon pluck'd back his foot, saying, <hi>It is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to follow many then few.</hi> So argued <hi>Jovinian</hi> against St. <hi>Hierome, Pauci pro vobis?</hi> You have but a few on your side: To whom he modestly answered, <hi>pauci steterunt pro Christo.</hi> They were but a few that stuck to Christ himself. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> professeth <hi>that no man stood to him.</hi> And <hi>Liberius</hi> a Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> being importun'd to turn <hi>Arrian</hi> upon this motive, <hi>Pene Omnes jam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senserunt.</hi> All in effect have now subscribed to <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme:</hi> Confidently answered <hi>Veritas, solitudine non mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitur:</hi> Truth is not weakned by paucitie of Professors. <hi>Elias</hi> stood up alone in the cause of God, and carried it against all the prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> and the Grove: so did <hi>Athanasius</hi> prevail at last against all the <hi>Arrian</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops. And when <hi>Philip Melancthon</hi> with some few more of the Reformers (as <hi>Sleidan</hi> reports) entreated <hi>Frederick</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> to abolish the private <hi>Masse,</hi> for divers good reasons then alledg'd, and urg'd; and the Duke replied, <hi>Pauci pro vobis?</hi> They stopt his mouth with this rejoynder; <hi>Semper major pars homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> &amp;c. The greatest part have ever resisted the truth.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:119235:23"/>
            <p>But what though in all places and ages, the greater part of the world hath resisted the truth, as <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambers</hi> withstood <hi>Moses?</hi> yet the <hi>Church of Christ</hi> hath alwayes had many <hi>members;</hi> as our Lord himself tels that <hi>Sceptick</hi> in the 13. chapter of Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> at the 29. verse, where to shew that his <hi>members</hi> are many in themselves, though but few in comparison of the Church malignant, he saith, <hi>That many shall come from the East, and from the West, and from the North, and from the South, and shall sit down with</hi> Abraham, Isaac <hi>and</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, <hi>in the Kingdome of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus having proved both that the <hi>body of Christs Church</hi> is but <hi>one;</hi> and yet that in this <hi>one body</hi> there be many <hi>members;</hi> It now onely remains that I shew how that be they nere so many, yet they are all <hi>members of one another;</hi> which is the last thing consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in our Apostles Reddition, and come now to be handled.</p>
            <p>As all the <hi>members</hi> of the <hi>body</hi> natural have not the same Office; but each of them having somewhat that the other lacks, it freely communicates to all the rest what it hath, and they stand in need of: so in the <hi>Church</hi> we are all <hi>members</hi> one of another; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Priest must study for the people, and the people must labour for the Priest: The civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate is to rule, and the Subjects are to obey: briefly, all must serve God in their several stations, and so contribute towards the welfare of the <hi>body mystical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore as in a Quire, some sing the Treble, others the Mean, others the counter-Tenor, others the Tenor, others the Base; and so, while they keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves exactly to their own parts, the Musick is sweet, and the Harmony complete: so in the <hi>Church,</hi> while
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119235:24"/> every one dischargeth his own duty, and conscientiously performs his own part; the whole <hi>Church</hi> flourisheth <hi>to the glory of God,</hi> and the general good.</p>
            <p>Here's all the difference, that the several <hi>members of the body natural</hi> so well agree, flowes from the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: but that all the <hi>members of Christ's body mystical</hi> so sweetly correspond, comes merely from <hi>the gift of Gods grace;</hi> and if any of these <hi>members</hi> agree not with the rest, as they should and ought, it is onely for want of Grace: and a foul sin and shame it must needs be unto us that are Christians, if the <hi>members of the body natural</hi> be more peaceable among themselves, and so more perfect then are <hi>the members of Christ's body mystical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And since it hath pleased the Holy Ghost here to make use of this comparison; and to bring in the body thus to teach the soul; it is our bounden duty, and should be our diligence, at least to observe and imitate, if not to exceed and excel the bodily <hi>members</hi> in our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian relations, and Spiritual performances each to other.</p>
            <p>First then as in the body natural, if the Head be in danger, the armes and hands will offer and expose themselves for to defend it: So in the <hi>body politick</hi> (which consists of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi>) The King is under God <hi>The supream Head in all Causes Ecclesiastical and Civil;</hi> and as <hi>Davids</hi> Worthies truly said to him, <hi>Worth ten thousand of us; He is the Light of our eyes, the Breath of our nostrils, and the Ioy of our hearts,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore should his sacred Majesty be in the least danger; He deserves not the name of a true <hi>Britan,</hi> (who have ever been justly honoured for their Courage and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty) and much lesse of a true <hi>Christian,</hi> who would not be prodigal of his blood in such an exigent, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119235:24"/> willingly ransome his Gracious Soveraigns Life, with the losse of his own.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As in the <hi>body natural</hi> the inferiour <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> envy not the the more Honourable neither do the Superiour <hi>members</hi> disdain their underlings: so in the <hi>Church,</hi> such as are sordidly ignorant should not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lign them that are eminently Learned: neither should the Learned despise those that are Ignorant. As our knowledge should not puffe us up, so our Charity should edifie others. The poor must not pine at the rich mans prosperity, neither should the rich insult o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the poor in their necessity, For as one God made them both, <hi>so he made the one for the other,</hi> saith <hi>Solomon.</hi> And the greatest Potentate on Earth may sometimes stand in need of the meanest Peasant; as in the Fable, <hi>The Mouse delivered the Lion, by gnawing the snare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, As in the <hi>body natural,</hi> if any <hi>one member</hi> be in pain, all the rest grieve and groan for company; for let but the Foot be prick'd, &amp; straight the Eyes weep; the Ears listen, the Head consults; the Tongue complains, the Heart akes; and the Hand, doth what it can to pick out the thorn: So should we all stand affected in the <hi>body mystical;</hi> we must sympathize in each others miseries. <hi>Who is afflicted</hi> saith our Apostle, <hi>and I burn not.</hi> And if he were so sensible of a single mans affliction, then how should we be wounded with the pressures and persecutions of the whole Church? If when only Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was imprison'd in the 12. chapter of the <hi>Acts,</hi> then <hi>prayers were made by the Church for him?</hi> Then how much more must the true <hi>members</hi> be pang'd, when the whole <hi>Church</hi> is either vexed by Tyranny, or rent in pieces by Schisme? <hi>Saul, Saul, why
<pb n="04" facs="tcp:119235:25"/> persecutest thou me?</hi> The Lord Christ was in his <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral body Triumphant in Heaven</hi> when he thus accosted <hi>Saul,</hi> and yet to shew how extremely sensible he was, of the injuries and indignities offered to <hi>his mystical bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> then on the Earth; he cryed out, <hi>why persecutest thou me?</hi> as if he still languished in all our troubles and bled at all our wounds.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, As in the <hi>body natural,</hi> if there be any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Vertue in, or Honour done to any <hi>one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> all the rest are equal sharers in it: If the Head be more politick, or the Tongue more perswasive, or the Hand more active and cunning in any kind them usual, then doth not the Heart rejoyce to think of it, and the Eare to hear of it? Yea, doth not the whole man shout, and stand on tiptoe for joy that he hath such a glitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Head, such an eloquent Tongue, such a dexterous Hand? &amp;c. In like manner we should chearfully impart all our gifts of grace to the benefit of our <hi>fellow members in the Church.</hi> In this kind, like the <hi>primitive Christians,</hi> we should have all in common; and as the Apostle speaks; <hi>No man should seek his own things, but every one should study to promote the cause of Christ.</hi> Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> taxes it as a fault in <hi>Acesius,</hi> one of the Ring-leaders of the <hi>Donatists,</hi> that he having found out, as he gloried, a nearer and shorter cut to Heaven, then any of the ancient Fathers ever heard of; when he was got up himself, he pluck'd away the Ladder, least any more should follow him. <hi>Et ab uno disce omnes,</hi> in him you see the nature of all <hi>Seperatists,</hi> who envy Heaven it self to all but their own Faction; and you may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that some of the late <hi>Phanaticks</hi> that were execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, died with imprecations in their mouthes, by which you may see of what Spirit they all are: But though
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119235:25"/>
               <hi>Israel</hi> play the Harlot, yet let not <hi>Judah</hi> sin, and what is reported in the <hi>Mythologie, that a blinde man and a lame Covenanted to live together; that so between the eyes of the one, and the Legs of the other, their personal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects might be mutually supplied,</hi> we that are true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, should in our several places labour to make good: we must (as <hi>Job</hi> speaks of himself) <hi>become Eyes to the blind, and Feet to the lame,</hi> and (as our Apostle did) <hi>all unto all:</hi> that so the <hi>body mystical</hi> may not lack what any particular <hi>member</hi> thereof hath; seeing that what ere we have, God hath given it us for the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as well as for our selves.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, As in the <hi>body natural,</hi> should the <hi>members</hi> fall out among themselves, so that the Hands should either strike the Head, scratch the Face, pluck out the Eyes, or tear off the Hair; or if the Teeth should either bite out the Tongue, or bite the flesh of the Armes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> would not all that saw or heard it judge the man to be stark mad, and pack him away to <hi>Bedlam?</hi> So in the <hi>body mystical</hi> of which we are all <hi>members,</hi> should there be any person or faction of so desperate principles, and so damnable in their practice, as to plot how to lay vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hands upon the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> whom God <hi>(as an inestimable blessing)</hi> hath made our <hi>Head and Governour;</hi> or to extirpate <hi>Episcopacy</hi> root and branch, which is all one as to pluck out <hi>the eyes of the Church,</hi> for the Holy Ghost hath made them our over-seers: or to abolish the publick <hi>Liturgy</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> with all its <hi>Ceremonies, Vestiments,</hi> and <hi>Ornaments,</hi> which is all one as to scratch the face, and tear off the haire <hi>of our Religion established:</hi> Or to silence and sequester the Loyall <hi>Orthodoxe Clergie,</hi> which is in effect as bad as biting out their tongues; or to bite off the flesh of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119235:26"/> their armes, by discoulouring and dispoyling the Loyal Gentry, and others that Ventured their lives, and fortunes, in the late just undertaking against <hi>Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> and all others that no less insolently then cause<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly rose up against lawful authority, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all such to be no better then persons distracted; sure they were mad for the time, and some of them still stand in need of Physick, as well as both our pity and prayers, that God would bring them to their wits again; and that he would <hi>abate their pride, asswage their malice, and confound their designes and devices,</hi> that so there may be no more carrying into captivity at home, or abroad, and no more complaining in our streets.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, As in the <hi>body natural</hi> should any of the <hi>members</hi> go about to bring in new waies of discharging their several offices, as some will stand on their heads, and walk on their hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The attempt must needs be look'd upon by all sober men as monstrous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it inverts the order of nature, and the endeav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, though never so well perform'd, would be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surd by the graver-sort to be very Ridiculous: So God is the God of order; and our Apostle wills <hi>that all things bee done decently and in Order:</hi> And therefore all such innovators, as either out of affectation, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, faction or interest, do despise the old, and labour to introduce new forms of administration in Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worship and service, preferring their own brain-sick inventions before the long experienc'd good wayes and rules of the Church of God; as they are both monstrous and ridiculous in themselves so they cannot chuse but be both odious, and abbominable in the sight of God, and all that are good.</p>
            <p>Seventhly As in the <hi>body natural,</hi> if <hi>one of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:119235:26"/> corrupt, and putrifie, the skillful and faithful Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgian is forced to cut it off without delay, least by a gangrene it destroy the whole: <hi>Ense rescindendum est, ne pars syncera trahatur.</hi> So in the Church if any go about by Heresie, Schism, and Sedition to infect, wire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, and withdraw their fellow-<hi>members</hi> from <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God, and Allegiance to his Anointed</hi> (as too many <hi>Phanaticks</hi> have done of late.) They must not only be rebuked, and shamefully discountenanc'd and discarded by Excommunications, Suspensions, Degradations, Deprivations, giving over unto Sathan, and such other <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> censures as properly fall under the power of the <hi>Keyes</hi> which our Savior cōmitted to his <hi>Church,</hi> (as knowing well that if the <hi>Church</hi> have no jurisdiction, no coertion in its power, there will be no conscience in the Peoples practice) but also if Schismatical and seditious Ring-leaders continue contumacious, and become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corigible, then they must be timely cut off by such cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral punishments, as by the law of God, and this Land, the Civil Magistrate is impowred to inflict upon such Capital Offenders; as in the 7. chapter of <hi>Ezra</hi> at the 26. verse, <hi>Whosoever will not do the Law of thy God, and the Law of thy King, let judgement be executed speedily upon him, whether it be unto death, or unto banishment, or to confiscation of goods, or to imprisonment.</hi> And Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> justifies that Sentence upon this ground, <hi>Melius est ut pereat unus, quam unitas.</hi> It is better one perish, then Unity.</p>
            <p>And we cannot but be sensible now that <hi>Impuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ad deteriora:</hi> as wise <hi>Solomon</hi> hath it in his <hi>Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, Because judgement is not executed speedily, therefore the heart of man is set to do evil,</hi> &amp;c. Some men who are bad enough by nature, have been so poysoned in their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119235:27"/> their Principles, by the iniquity and indulgence of these Times, that they neither will nor can live under any Law, but what their own licentiousness propounds to it self in their clandestine meetings, in which their preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is but plotting how to blow up both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> like the men of the Gunpowder Gospel, which made choice of a Vault. In their Declaration they cry up <hi>King Jesus,</hi> when they would pluck down his <hi>Christ,</hi> I mean his <hi>Anointed;</hi> and they call their <hi>Rebellion Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> and their <hi>Conspiracy, Conscience.</hi> They know that as silly as some of the cōmon people are, yet they will not easily be induced to swallow the hook of such Villany, unlesse it be speciously baited with the shew of <hi>Gods Cause,</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi>'s <hi>Call:</hi> though the Devil begets the Brat, yet they will have God himseif to father it. The Civil Magistrates mercy fleshes these to do more mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, who like so many mad Oxen, kill him that is next, and destroy without distinction: and if they be not prevented will set all on fire, though they are sure to be consumed in the flame. There is no dallying with such Desperado's as these <hi>Jesuited Phanaticks:</hi> you have too long cherished these Serpents in your bosomes, which now not only hisse, but spit the poyson of defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in your faces. Forget not the Proverb, <hi>Pitie spoiles a Citie:</hi> then take these brats of <hi>Babel,</hi> and pay them in their own Coin: <hi>Nec Lex est justior ulla, quam,</hi> &amp;c. The speedy execution of justice is the most convincing, and only unanswerable argument to be used and urged against such Traytors, as like <hi>Medlers</hi> will never be good till they be rotten; they may miscal themselves Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, but they act, &amp; suffer as the worst of Malefactours.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, As in the <hi>body natural,</hi> the <hi>members</hi> abhor nothing more then to be rent and torn piece-mele each
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119235:27"/> from other, as we read in Ecclesiastical History, that during the ten Persecutions, some Christians were cast to hunger-starv'd Lyons; and others were tied by the arms and legs to the tails of wild horses, that so they might be torn in pieces: In like manner in the <hi>Church</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more dreadful then to observe how many poor <hi>members</hi> of Christs body mystical have been violently distorted, and drawn as it were a pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, each from other, all of them from Christ, by such wilful Schismes, and wicked Separations as have within some few years been made amongst us. The <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Historians</hi> report of a Gulph which happened in <hi>Rome,</hi> and could not be closed till some noble <hi>Roman</hi> in love to his Country did cast himself into it▪ whereupon <hi>Quintus Curtius</hi> having armed himself <hi>Cap-a-pee,</hi> did ride full speed, and threw himself in; and the <hi>Roman</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies threw their Gold Chains into it after him, thereby worthily crowning so renowned a Fact: But now alass, the Times are so changed for the worse, that it is the chief work and glory of many to make gaps of separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and gulphs of division in the Church, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was like <hi>Ierusalem</hi> at unity within it self; and some both of our City and Country Ladies, by their leave, will have none to be their Chaplains, but onely such noted Sectaries, and notorious Schismaticks as shall not sit down with them at table, till they have in a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winded Grace given God thanks for the numerous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of the Brethren and Sisters of the pure and Holy Separation.</p>
            <p>And though our Apostle (in the 16. Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi> at the 17. Verse) gives this special Caveat, <hi>observe them who cause division among you, and avoyd them:</hi> Yet now who sees not that too many observe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119235:28"/> the Sowers of discord and division, that they may the better side with them; because they see with no smal content some that have been forward Seedsmen in that kind, now not only pardon'd but preferr'd: and when Schisme and Sedition prove the high way to promotion, sure, that new-found-road will never want store of Travellers, which in time will prove troublers both of Church and State, and I could tell you how malapert some of them are grown already in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, but that for travailing too near the heels of truth, some have had their Teeth beaten out.</p>
            <p>There be Six things (saith <hi>Solomon</hi> in the 6. Chap. of the <hi>Proverbs</hi>) which God hates, and his Soul ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors the Seventh; <hi>and that is he which sowes discord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong brethren:</hi> and there is a great deal of reason why God and men should abhor him: for,</p>
            <p>First, <hi>This soweing of discord</hi> is a vice opposite to <hi>Charity,</hi> which our Apostle (in the 13. Chapter of the first Epistle to the <hi>Corinthians) prefers not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moral vertues, but the Teological graces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Hereby is bred not only <hi>the hatred of some one,</hi> but even of <hi>Unity it self.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, This <hi>Sin,</hi> like the plague of Pestilence, insects all that come but near it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is contrary <hi>to peace,</hi> which is the cheif earthly good; and therefore the Jews when they wish'd well to each other, used this both for their Salutation, and Valediction, <hi>Peace be to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, It divides such as are join'd together nearer then man and wife, even the <hi>Members of the same body mystical;</hi> then which as nothing can be more painful, so of all other miseries and mischeifs; it is the most dreadful: and upon these grounds St. <hi>Augustine</hi> first
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119235:28"/> mourn'd in secret for such unchristian, and indeed <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristian</hi> divisions; and then censur'd the authors thereof to be worse then the very Tormentors of Christ himself upon the Crosse: <hi>Venit Persecutor</hi> (saith he) <hi>&amp; non fregit Crura Christi,</hi> &amp;c. The Persecutor came and did not break Christs Legs hanging on the Crosse; but <hi>Donatus</hi> came (he speaks of the Schismatick) and rent his Church in peices; the natural body of Christ was whole in the hands of his Tormentors, and yet <hi>his body mystical</hi> (which he loved much more then his natural, for he gave this to save that) is not whole among us who professe our selves christians.</p>
            <p>Lastly, as in the body natural, nothing is more useful and graceful then the right and proper placing of every <hi>Member;</hi> so is it also in the body mystical; in which God hath appointed every man his proper cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and particular function, in which he is to abide, and to which he is wholly to apply himself, as Gods sanction; and which he that transgresseth, sins with an high hand against Gods expresse Ordinance, and paves the way to anarchy and confusion.</p>
            <p>Then to wind up all, let us humbly and heartily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech the Lord to give unto all <hi>the Members of his Church,</hi> comelinesse, quietnesse, and order; that so Evangelical purity, which was both the beauty, and glory of our first Reformation, may not ere long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into profanesse, our Churches into conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and our spiritual Union into civil dissention; from which, <hi>Good Lord deliver us:</hi> and give us all Grace in our distinct callings (as the most propable means to prevent these imminent mischeifs) to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the <hi>bodily members;</hi> in the faithful and peaceable
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119235:29"/> discharge of our duties; and so to deal with all other Christians in our respective places, as if they were as near and dear unto us, as are our own natural Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Now to God the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>